Anna Fariha

Kahlert School of Computing University of Utah

♥ Warnock Engineering Building, #2851

72 Central Campus Drive, Salt Lake City, UT, 84112

Research Interests

The aim of my research is to democratize data and data-driven systems towards boosting productivity and enhancing transparency. To this end, my research focuses on three key aspects of data system democratization: *enhancing usability* of data systems for both non-experts and experts, *providing explanation frameworks* to enable understanding of system behavior, and *achieving trust and fairness* in data-driven machine learning.

- Data systems usability: query by example, data summarization, data discovery, data-wrangling recommendation, data evolution.
- Metadata management and its applications: data constraints, data drift, data cleaning.
- Systems for machine learning and AI: trusted machine learning, fair machine learning, explainable AI, personalized text summarization, large language models for data wrangling.
- Causal reasoning and explanation frameworks: software debugging, automatic program repair, data debugging, explaining data non-conformance.

Education

Doctor of Philosophy in Computer Science

2021

Manning College of Information and Computer Sciences

University of Massachusetts, Amherst, MA

- Dissertation: Enhancing Usability and Explainability of Data Systems
- Advisor: Alexandra Meliou
- Committee members: Emery Berger, Peter Haas, Suman Nath
- CGPA: 4.00 out of 4.00

Master of Science in Computer Science

2020

Manning College of Information and Computer Sciences

University of Massachusetts, Amherst, MA

- CGPA: 4.00 out of 4.00

Master of Science in Computer Science and Engineering

2011

Department of Computer Science and Engineering

University of Dhaka, Bangladesh

- Thesis: A New Approach for Frequent Human Interaction Pattern Mining in Meeting Databases
- Advisor: Suraiya Pervin
- CGPA: 4.00 out of 4.00

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science and Engineering

2010

Department of Computer Science and Engineering

University of Dhaka, Bangladesh

- Thesis: An Algorithm for Graph Mining using Efficient Graph Indexing for Evolving Database
- Advisor: Chowdhury Farhan Ahmed
- CGPA: 3.83 out of 4.00

Employment History

University of Utah

Assistant Professor

Salt Lake City, UT, USA

Kahlert School of Computing

Microsoft 6/2021 – 5/2023

Redmond, WA, USA

PROSE research and engineering team for AI-assisted programming

Managers: Gustavo Soares, Sumit Gulwani

Microsoft 5/2019 – 11/2019

Research Intern

Bellevue, WA, USA

PROSE research and engineering team for AI-assisted programming

Mentor: Ashish Tiwari

Project: Conformance constraints and trusted machine learning

Microsoft Research 5/2018 – 8/2018

Research Intern Redmond, WA, USA

Data Management, Exploration and Mining (DMX)

Mentor: Suman Nath

Project: Adaptive interventional debugging for finding root causes of nondeterministic software bugs

University of Massachusetts 9/2016 – 5/2021

Research Assistant Amherst, MA, USA

Data Systems Research for Exploration, Analytics, and Modeling (DREAM) Lab

Manning College of Information and Computer Sciences

Supervisor: Alexandra Meliou

Lalmatia Women's College 1/2015 – 4/2015

Guest Lecturer Dhaka, Bangladesh

Department of Business Administration

University of Dhaka 5/2014 – 8/2016

Lecturer Dhaka, Bangladesh

Department of Computer Science and Engineering

United International University 5/2012 – 4/2014

Lecturer Dhaka, Bangladesh

Department of Computer Science and Engineering

University of Liberal Arts 10/2011 – 1/2012

Competitive Programming Trainer Dhaka, Bangladesh

Coach for competitive programming in preparation for ACM ICPC Programming Contests

Structured Data Systems Limited 9/2011 – 5/2012

Software Engineer Dhaka, Bangladesh

Android and Blackberry mobile applications

University of Asia Pacific 10/2010 – 10/2010

Competitive Programming Trainer Dhaka, Bangladesh

Coach for competitive programming in preparation for ACM ICPC Programming Contests

Honors, Awards, & Achievements

SIGMOD Distinguished PC member	2023
SIGMOD Distinguished PC member	2022
SIGMOD Comprehensive Reproducibility Award	2022
VLDB Best Demonstration Runner-up Award	2020
Jim Gray Scholarship, CICS, UMass Amherst	2016
Special Achievement Award: Bangladesh ICT Journalist Forum	2012
Special Achievement Award: Bangladesh Bangladesh Women in IT	2012
University Scholarship for result in Bachelors of Science, U of Dhaka	2012
Special Achievement Award for outstanding performances in programming contests, U of Dhaka	2011
Dean's Honor Award (top 1%), Faculty of Engineering, U of Dhaka	2011
Dean's Award, Faculty of Engineering, U of Dhaka	2010
Fatema-Iqbal Trust Scholarship, U of Dhaka	2008
National Education Board General Scholarship (12th grade)	2006
Special Achievement Award for Higher Secondary Result, Kushtia District Council	2006
National Education Board Talent Pool Scholarship (10th grade)	2004
Best Student of the School (Kushtia Govt. Girls' High School)	2003
National Education Board Talent Pool Scholarship (8th grade)	2001
National Education Board Talent Pool Scholarship (5th grade)	1998
Travel and Accommodation Scholarships	
Invited Participant with Accommodation Support, Logic and Algebra for Query Evaluation	2023
 Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing, Berkeley, California 	
Invited Participant with Travel & Accommodation Support, CRA-WP Career Mentoring Workshop	2023
- Chicago, Illinois	
CRA-W Grad Cohort Workshop Travel and Accommodation Award, Washington DC	2017
Programming Contests	
Rank 5, ACM International Collegiate Programming Contest, Dhaka (Team: DU Resonance)	2011
Rank 1, Islamic University of Technology ICT Fest Programming Contest (Team: DU Resonance)	2011
Rank 1, Dhaka University National Collegiate Programming Contest (Team: DU Resonance)	2011
Rank 1, Dhaka University National Collegiate Programming Contest [Women] (Team: DU Felicity)	2011
Rank 2, SUST National Collegiate Programming Contest (Team: DU Resonance)	2010
Rank 6, ACM International Collegiate Programming Contest, Amritapuri (Team: DU Resonance)	2010
Rank 4, ACM International Collegiate Programming Contest, Dhaka (Team: DU Resonance)	2010
Rank 3, ACM International Collegiate Programming Contest, Dhaka (Team: DU Ouranos)	2009
Rank 515, Google Code Jam, (Individual, id: chorui12)	2009
Rank 4, AUST National Collegiate Programming Contest (Team: DU Resonance)	2009

Grants

Enhancing Usability and Explainability of Data Systems

Microsoft Research Dissertation Grant \$25,000 USD

Academic year 2020-2021

Training the Next Generation of Database Engineers: Responsible, User-Centric, and Efficient Data Management

USHE: Computer Science Targeted Workforce Application

Academic year 2023-2024

Teaching grant for developing new course: Human-centered Data Management

Publications

Journal and Conference Publications

- [1] Anjali Singh, Anna Fariha, Christopher Brooks, Gustavo Soares, Austin Henley, Ashish Tiwari, Chethan M, Heeryung Choi, and Sumit Gulwani. Investigating student mistakes in introductory data science programming. In SIGCSE 2024: The 55th ACM Technical Symposium on Computer Science Education, Portland, OR, USA, March 20-23, 2024. ACM, 2024
- [2] Rohan Bavishi, Harshit Joshi, José Cambronero, Anna Fariha, Sumit Gulwani, Vu Le, Ivan Radicek, and Ashish Tiwari. Neurosymbolic repair for low-code formula languages. *Proc. ACM Program. Lang.*, 6(OOPSLA2):1093–1122, 2022
- [3] Sainyam Galhotra, Anna Fariha, Raoni Lourenço, Juliana Freire, Alexandra Meliou, and Divesh Srivastava. Dataprism: Exposing disconnect between data and systems. In SIGMOD '22: International Conference on Management of Data, Philadelphia, PA, USA, June 12 17, 2022, pages 217–231. ACM, 2022
- [4] Maliha Tashfia Islam, Anna Fariha, Alexandra Meliou, and Babak Salimi. Through the data management lens: Experimental analysis and evaluation of fair classification. In *SIGMOD '22: International Conference on Management of Data, Philadelphia, PA, USA, June 12 17, 2022*, pages 232–246. ACM, 2022
- [5] Anna Fariha, Ashish Tiwari, Arjun Radhakrishna, Sumit Gulwani, and Alexandra Meliou. Conformance constraint discovery: Measuring trust in data-driven systems. In SIGMOD '21: International Conference on Management of Data, Virtual Event, China, June 20-25, 2021, pages 499–512. ACM, 2021
- [6] Anna Fariha, Suman Nath, and Alexandra Meliou. Causality-guided adaptive interventional debugging. In *Proceedings of the 2020 International Conference on Management of Data, SIGMOD Conference 2020, online conference, June 14-19, 2020*, pages 431–446. ACM, 2020 (ACM SIGMOD Comprehensive Reproducibility Award)
- [7] Anna Fariha and Alexandra Meliou. Example-driven query intent discovery: Abductive reasoning using semantic similarity. *Proc. VLDB Endow.*, 12(11):1262–1275, 2019
- [8] Anna Fariha, Chowdhury Farhan Ahmed, Carson K. Leung, Md. Samiullah, Suraiya Pervin, and Longbing Cao. A new framework for mining frequent interaction patterns from meeting databases. *Eng. Appl. Artif. Intell.*, 45:103–118, 2015
- [9] Amit Mandal, Mehedi Hasan, Anna Fariha, and Chowdhury Farhan Ahmed. GSCS graph stream classification with side information. In *APWeb*, pages 389–400, 2015
- [10] Md. Samiullah, Chowdhury Farhan Ahmed, Anna Fariha, Md. Rafiqul Islam, and Nicolas Lachiche. Mining frequent correlated graphs with a new measure. *Expert Syst. Appl.*, 41(4):1847–1863, 2014
- [11] Shafaet Ashraf, Sheikh Muhammad Sarwar, Md. Abeed Hassan, Saifuddin Md. Tareeq, and Anna Fariha. An efficient method for extracting subtrees against forest query. In *Proceedings of the 9th International Conference on Ubiquitous Information Management and Communication, IMCOM 2015, Bali, Indonesia, January 08 10, 2015*, pages 98:1–98:7. ACM, 2015
- [12] Anna Fariha, Chowdhury Farhan Ahmed, Carson Kai-Sang Leung, S. M. Abdullah, and Longbing Cao. Mining frequent patterns from human interactions in meetings using directed acyclic graphs. In *PAKDD*, pages 38–49, 2013
- [13] Md. Samiullah, Chowdhury Farhan Ahmed, Manziba Akanda Nishi, Anna Fariha, S. M. Abdullah, and Md. Rafiqul Islam. Correlation mining in graph databases with a new measure. In *APWeb*, pages 88–95, 2013
- [14] Shariful Islam, Anna Fariha, Chowdhury Farhan Ahmed, and Byeong-Soo Jeong. EGDIM: evolving graph database indexing method. In *ICUIMC*, pages 56:1–56:10, 2012

Short, Demonstration, and Workshop Papers

[15] Bhavya Chopra, Anna Fariha, Sumit Gulwani, Austin Z. Henley, Daniel Perelman, Mohammad Raza, Sherry Shi, Danny Simmons, and Ashish Tiwari. CoWrangler: Recommender System for Data-Wrangling Scripts. In SIGMOD '23: International Conference on Management of Data, Seattle, USA, June 18-23, 2023. ACM, 2023

- [16] El Kindi Rezig, Anshul Bhandari, Anna Fariha, Benjamin Price, Allan Vanterpool, Andrew Bowne, Lindsey McEvoy, and Vijay Gadepally. Examples are all you need: Iterative data discovery by example in data lakes. 2022
- [17] El Kindi Rezig, Anshul Bhandari, Anna Fariha, Benjamin Price, Allan Vanterpool, Vijay Gadepally, and Michael Stonebraker. DICE: data discovery by example. *PVLDB*, 14(12):2819–2822, 2021
- [18] Nishant Yadav, Matteo Brucato, Anna Fariha, Oscar Youngquist, Julian Killingback, Alexandra Meliou, and Peter Haas. SUBSUME: A dataset for subjective summary extraction from Wikipedia documents. pages 131–141, November 2021
- [19] Anna Fariha, Ashish Tiwari, Alexandra Meliou, Arjun Radhakrishna, and Sumit Gulwani. CoCo: Interactive Exploration of Conformance Constraints for Data Understanding and Data Cleaning. In SIGMOD '21: International Conference on Management of Data, Virtual Event, China, June 20-25, 2021, pages 2706–2710. ACM, 2021
- [20] Anna Fariha, Ashish Tiwari, Arjun Radhakrishna, and Sumit Gulwani. ExTuNe: Explaining Tuple Non-conformance. In *Proceedings of the 2020 International Conference on Management of Data, SIGMOD Conference 2020, online conference, June 14-19, 2020*, pages 2741–2744. ACM, 2020
- [21] Anna Fariha, Matteo Brucato, Peter J. Haas, and Alexandra Meliou. SuDocu: Summarizing Documents by Example. *Proc. VLDB Endow.*, 13(12):2861–2864, 2020 (Best Demonstration Runner Up Award)
- [22] Anna Fariha, Sheikh Muhammad Sarwar, and Alexandra Meliou. SQuID: Semantic Similarity-Aware Query Intent Discovery. In *Proceedings of the 2018 International Conference on Management of Data, SIGMOD Conference 2018, Houston, TX, USA, June 10-15, 2018*, pages 1745–1748. ACM, 2018
- [23] Quazi Marufur Rahman, Anna Fariha, Amit Mandal, Chowdhury Farhan Ahmed, and Carson K. Leung. A Sliding Window-Based Algorithm for Detecting Leaders from Social Network Action Streams. In *IEEE/WIC/ACM WI-IAT*, pages 133–136, 2015

PhD Thesis

[24] Anna Fariha. *Enhancing Usability and Explainability of Data Systems*. PhD thesis, University of Massachusetts Amherst. https://scholarworks.umass.edu/dissertations_2/2311/

Invited Talks

- Recent Trends in Scalable and Human-centric Data Systems
 - Research Challenges in Computing Seminar Series, University of Utah

October, 2023

- Through the Data Management Lens: Experimental Analysis and Evaluation of Fair Classification
 - Bias, Ethics and Trustworthiness in Data Science and AI event, University of Utah

September, 2023

- Blame the data, not the system: how data constraints can help in trustworthy machine learning and explain causes of data-system malfunction
 - Data Science Lecture Series, University of Utah

September, 2023

- University of Washington, Northwest Database Society

November, 2021

- Blame the data, not the system: How data profiles can help explain causes of data-system malfunction
 - Northwest Database Society (NWDS) Annual Meeting

May, 2023

• Enhancing usability and explainability of data systems

 Northwest Database Society (NWDS) Annual Meeting 	May, 2023
 Database Seminar, University of California San Diego (virtual) 	April, 2023
- Cornell University	April, 2022
- Georgia University of Technology	April, 2022
- University of California, Santa Barbara	March, 2022
- University of Minnesota (virtual)	March, 2022
- University of Waterloo (virtual)	March, 2022

 University of Utah 	February, 2022
- University of Toronto (virtual)	February, 2022
- Pennsylvania State University (virtual)	February, 2022
- EPIC meeting, University of California, Berkeley (virtual)	February, 2022
- Ohio State University (virtual)	January, 2022
 CSAIL, Massachusetts Institute of Technology (virtual) 	October, 2021
- Microsoft (virtual)	January, 2021
- Megagon Labs (virtual)	February, 2021
- University of Pennsylvania (virtual)	February, 2021
 DATA Lab, Northeastern University (virtual) 	January, 2021

Teaching

· University of Utah

- CS 5353/6353 - Deep Learning (undergraduate + graduate)	Fall 2023
- CS 3960/6959 - Human-Centered Data Management (undergraduate + graduate)	Spring 2024

· University of Dhaka, Bangladesh

 CSE 1201 - Fundamentals of Programming (undergraduate) 	Spring 2014
 CSE 1211 - Fundamentals of Programming Lab (undergraduate) 	Spring 2014
 CSE 1102 - Discrete Mathematics (undergraduate) 	Fall 2014
 CSE 2101 - Data Structures and Algorithms (undergraduate) 	Spring 2015
 CSE 2111 - Data Structures and Algorithms Lab (undergraduate) 	Spring 2015
 CSE 3113 - Microprocessor and Assembly Language Lab (undergraduate) 	Fall 2015
 CSE 1111 - Fundamentals of Computer and Computing Lab (undergraduate) 	Fall 2015
 CSE 2112 - Object Oriented Programming Lab (undergraduate) 	Spring 2016
 CSE 2212 - Design and Analysis of Algorithms Lab (undergraduate) 	Spring 2016
- CSE 4111 - Artificial Intelligence Lab (undergraduate)	Spring 2016

· United International University, Bangladesh

- CSI 219 Discrete Mathematics (undergraduate)
- CSI 121 Structured Programming Language (undergraduate)
- CSI 122 Structured Programming Language Laboratory (undergraduate)
- CSI 228 Algorithms Laboratory (undergraduate)
- CSI 233 Theory of Computing (undergraduate)
- CSI 341 Artificial Intelligence (undergraduate)
- CSI 342 Artificial Intelligence Laboratory (undergraduate)

Student Supervision

PhD Advisor

- Shiyi He
- Whanhee Cho

Masters & Undergraduate Advisor

- · University of Utah
 - Qiaoyi Cai
- · University of Dhaka

- Quazi Marufur Rahman (MS)	2015
- Amit Mandal	2015
- Mehedi Hasan	2015

Nitish Ranjan BhowmikKazi Mazbah Uddin	2015 2015
Mentorship	
University of Massachusetts Amherst	
 Maliha Islam (PhD) [Now at Microsoft] Hasnain Heickal (PhD) Oscar Youngquist (MS) Julian Killingback (MS) Kanchi Masalia (MS) Genglin Liu (Undergrad) Lucy Cousins (Undergrad) Armand Asnani (Undergrad) Nischal Dave (Undergrad) Zoey (Jingyi) Sun (Undergrad from Smith College) Lauren Beryl Larson (REU) (Undergrad from Wellesley College) Michael Satanovsky (High-school Intern from Hopkins School) 	2020–2021 2021–2022 2021–2022 2021 2020 2020
• Microsoft	
 Chethan Mahadevaswamy (Predoctoral Research Fellow) Bhavya Chopra (Predoctoral Research Fellow) Yang Shi (PhD student at North Carolina State University) 	2021–2022 2022–2023 2022
Professional Services	
Panelist	
 NSF Information and Intelligent Systems division (IIS) NSF's CSGrad4US Panel: "What I wish I knew before I started graduate school", Virtual SIGMOD New Researcher Symposium, Philadelphia, USA VLDB Round Table Chair: Interactive Querying and Visualization for Large Data (virtual) 	2023 October, 2023 June, 2022 August, 2021
Program Committee	_
 IEEE International Conference on Data Engineering (ICDE) (demo track) ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data (demo track) ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data (research track) IEEE International Conference on Data Engineering (ICDE) (Ph.D. Symposium) ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data (research track) International Conference on Very Large Databases (VLDB) (research track) ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data (research track) International Conference on Very Large Databases (VLDB) (research track) International Conference on Extending Database Technology (EDBT) (demonstration track) ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data (research track) International Conference on Extending Database Technology (EDBT) (demonstration track) International Conference on Very Large Databases (VLDB) (demonstration track) International Conference on Very Large Databases (VLDB) (demonstration track) 	2024 2024 2024 2023 2023 2023 2022 2022
Other Reviewing Service	
 Reviewer of the VLDB Journal Reviewer of User Interface Software and Technology (UIST) Session chair at International Conference on Extending Database Technology (EDBT) Reviewer of the VLDB Journal External reviewer of ACM CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems External reviewer of ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data External reviewer of ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data 	2023 2021 2021 2021 2021 2020 2019

• External reviewer of ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data	2018
Problem Setter & Judge of Competitive Programming Contests	
State University Bangladesh Inter-University Programming Contest, Bangladesh	2015
SAARC Programming Contest, Bangladesh University, Bangladesh	2014
Islamic University of Technology ICT Fest, Bangladesh	2014
SAARC Programming Contest, Bangladesh University, Bangladesh	2013
Bangladesh Informatics Olympiad, National Round, Bangladesh	2013
North South University Inter-University Programming Contest, Bangladesh	2013
ACM International Collegiate Programming Contest, Dhaka, Bangladesh	2012
Internal Service	
Faculty Advisor, Women in Computing at the University of Utah	2023–presen
Mentor of 1st Year PhD Student (Ishrat Jahan Eliza)	2023–presen
• Co-founder of UtahDB Research Center (URL: https://mod.cs.utah.edu)	2022–presen